主席。
不過。
五年過咗去。
二零一六年嘅。
以恆基為例。
真係唏噓啦嚇，即係。
五大發展商再加埋港鐵。
當時係中元指數一零零點六，而家係一四四點九一。
公屋咧就係由二零一二年嘅二點六年去到而家啱啱公佈嘅數字四點七年。
加加埋埋就有四十七萬個單位。如果啲單位係四百五十尺嘅咧，佢哋加埋七十四萬個單位。
噉啊，梁振英又好叻㗎，喺幾年前就係用呢一個重中之重嘅房屋政策咧，就冧掂好多香港人，就話佢可以解決呢個問題。
配套九龍東係唔可能成為一個新嘅商業中心。主席，我僅此陳詞，請局長要認真考慮呢啲問題。多謝主席。國家企業。
當我哋呢一個講緊呢個施政報告嘅時候咧，就幾大嘅候選人就喺度講緊宏圖大計，其中一樣嘢係講房屋。
到到二零一六年落成嘅公屋單位係五萬一千三百七十三，距離目標爭二萬四。私營市場嘅價格咧就喺梁振英任內升咗百分之四十四點八。
啊！譬如喺佢個當時就講話，香港唔係冇地，係好多地喺度晒陽。中地要加快用。又講過咧，提高住人均嘅住屋嘅面積，甚至咧非長者一人申請個公屋輪候咧，要三年。
噉啊，政府一一定話係冇地冇樓㗎，噉你某程度上咧都啱嘅，因為政府揸個土地好少。政府而家個土地咧，根據統計咧，如果係起到以七百尺嘅單位為例咧，就可以起到十二萬二千，即係土政府嘅土地庫。
購入。
點解唔做？
行基。
平方尺。
淨係呢幾年。
轉移視線，偷換概念。
恆基喺香港有四千萬。
新鴻基就係三千萬平方尺。
所講嘅所謂點點樣要喺？
我想講呢一啲嘅例子，即係話政府唔係冇地。
誒講緊嘅郊野公園咧，其實係。
喺東大宇啊，或者好多要拎走嗰啲，包括。
同埋新鴻基購入五年啊，購入嘅地咧係可以起七十一個大球場。
其實政府同發展商咧係跳緊一啲探窩，高地價政策。
政府就隨住政府嘅東北發展同埋新界西嘅發展咧，其實呢啲地產商咧已經早著先機嘅。
如果政府係肯面對呢一啲囤積嘅土地，係用政策上包括係要處罰呢一啲嘅土地；如果佢哋係改變農地係冇用嘅，將將佢還原，甚至係將呢啲土地咧係要發展成為收地成為公屋或者係居屋。
利益集團。
呢個政府？
喺國內嚟嘅。
懶理你普通市民去死。
係政府做唔講嘅嘢。
再加上而家嘅地產商越嚟越多，已經係。
係炒到咧，係破紀錄嘅天價。
價錢係幾多咧？平均嘅劏房價係四千零九十四蚊。
因為政府同埋地產商已經成為一個咧係共同嘅。
不斷係講大話，不過最令我哋擔心嘅就係而家啲。
所以我哋話要解決呢個房屋問題咧，係凍過水，凍過冰。
政府亦都無力係對抗地產商嘅囤積，亦都更加冇意思咁做。
亦都配合好多嘅北水嚟，最近啟德嘅幾幅發展地就係一啲大陸嚟嘅，係國企嚟。
政府係唔會理，因為事實上呢一啲嘅做法，可能亦都係政府係最容易咧去解決財政收入嘅一個方法。
特首嘅候選人包括而家呢個六六八九二點零嘅林鄭咧，已經有幾大地地產商咧，同埋啲大地主咧出嚟係要支持佢。
所以五年內嘅劏房嘅數字係應去到超過八萬七千人，八萬七千户係住咗接近二十萬人。劏房面積係十三一百三十二點九。
主席。
去。
誒國力。
黃碧雲議員。
本人僅此陳詞。
亦都燃料，醬咧。
政府嘅對手兩大嘅電力公司咧。
係一路咧，係作為咧，係對沖。
呢個就係政府，呢個就係政府還畀我哋呢五年嘅所謂房屋政策。
令佢唔會減電費嘅最好嘅一個做法，所以要求政府。
係儲足彈藥，用曬所有人力物力，同政府去周旋。
民企甚至國企，更加就唔可以觸動國企，我哋中央政府嘅企業嘅利益。
改善房屋問題，或者要求政府改善呢個土地問題，佢除咗咧喺度噏一啲係不切實際嘅。
畫餅充飢嘅，或者係要大幅度咧一路繼續係掟啲錢落去去做一啲嘅假大空工程以外咧，佢唔會答你。
另外咧，我就想講少少有關於電力點解咧？因為每一次咧，當我哋嘅電力管制協議完嘅時候咧，就係一個政呢個一屆嘅政府嘅差唔多要完結啦，今次都唔例外。
但係而家嘅利潤管制協議咧，就係畀咗電力公司魔術品，因為只要佢不斷增加個固定資產投資，包括係利用一啲新嘅能源嘅組合所需要嘅儲存啊、道誒嗰啲通道啊等等咧，就可以一路賺到盡。
主席。
食水含鉛超標調查委員會，舊年。
咁喺呢啲嘅建議，然又再以尚待落實嘅時候咧。
喺誒呢個環節，我想講一講關於食水安全嘅問題。
政府咧係公開交代，究竟當中發生咗乜嘢問題？點解仲會有水喉嘅工人？
今次啊，經過我哋睇嘅報道咧，就話發現又係懸空咧，係含鉛嘅焊料造成。
係用一啲含鉛嘅飼料去做一啲食水喉嘅更換工程，究竟又係邊個買料畀佢哋？係買一啲含鉛嘅飼料畀佢哋做咧？
更加咧，我相信咧，政府係冇幫到喺呢間工廠大廈裏邊工作或者係生活嘅市民，係檢驗血液有冇含鉛超標。
咁成個過程，我哋而家都唔知道喺邊一個環節出咗問題，所以我好希望政府咧係公開啲、透明一啲，等公眾理解究竟我哋嘅政策喺邊度仍然係有漏洞，究竟係。
組織監察水務署嘅表現同埋水質；四、借鑑海外經驗制定水質標準；五、推行水安全計劃，同埋六設計水喉安裝嘅登記發牌制度等等。
呢啲嘅事件啦，令我哋驚覺政府喺源水事件被揭發之後咧，你哋所採取嘅措施係未足以掃除公進公眾對於食水係咪含源呢一啲嘅疑慮嘅。
五月嘅時候發表咗報告，報告裏邊係提出咗十七項建議，咁主要包括誒一主動為所有公屋再安排食水測試，包括咧收集淨水嘅樣本；第二檢討現行法例框架同埋規管嘅制度；三設立獨立。
誒，我哋咧喺四日之前咧係睇到有報道，係話九龍中有一啲翻修嘅工廠大廈係做完換喉工程之後咧，喺抽水板化驗係發現食水含鉛量係超出標準嘅，源水又嚟啦。
嗱，水務署咧就冇公佈到係九龍中邊一間工廠大廈，咁所以其實咧同區嘅其他工廠大廈嗰啲人咧，其實都好擔心，亦都冇公佈究竟超標咗幾多，有幾多個水板驗咗出嚟之後發現超標，呢啲數據我哋完全唔知嘅。
究竟九龍中嘅呢一個工廠大廈係咪只係冰山一角咧？究竟仲有幾多新建嘅大廈、學校或者係私樓喺佢哋做維修或者新建造嘅工程，其實佢哋出嚟之後嘅水都會受到污染咧。我哋完全咧係冇。
冇呢啲嘅數據，公眾根本係唔知道究竟呢個措施係咪有效。如果政府已經採取嘅措施係足以保障食水安全，解決咗源水嘅問題嘅話咧，噉就冇理由係會再揾到係有食水含鉛超標嘅情況出現嘅。咁所以，我好希望咧。
有冇搞錯啊？
仲好笑喎！嗱，今日我哋有運防局局長喺度，嗱呢個咧係跨局嘅問題嚟嘅。
瞓完覺，朝頭早起身，開水喉放翻兩分鐘水先。如果你放長假期喺屋企嘅水喉冇用過咧，你再放多幾分鐘水。
邊一方面嘅問題咧？而家好明顯，而家係啲料有問題。第二人有問題啦，點解啲人係會用一啲唔應該用嘅料去做呢啲工程咧？
嘅水質把關上邊咧，我哋唔應該淪為第三世界國家。我哋只係唔使飲一啲好污糟邋遢嘅水，但係我哋會飲咗一啲重金屬。
所以你喺度拖，你係畀唔到公眾一個誠意。政府咧就講就話我哋係會跟進啊，我哋會全力跟進，但係你就我係睇到你係喺度全力拖延。
我哋驗水抽水班嘅方法就係用翻我哋過去一路民主黨認為好有問題嘅方法，就係話你又再放兩至五分鐘，然後先至攞嗰啲水嘛，再去化驗啊嘛，噉你又咪揾嚟做啊，揾嚟搞啊，根本就冇用。
叫政府盡快再為公屋咧安排嗰個食水嘅測試，係抽靜止嘅水板有幾難啊！叫你再翻去公屋嗰度抽一啲靜止嘅水板，你都要拖到話三月之後啦，過埋特首選舉先至搞啦。
水務處嘅喎，水務處到而家為止都係用緊放水兩至五分鐘先抽水板，噉你又盲目噉啊跟水務處，水務處就話啊我都唔知點，等國際專家先，噉你呢個政府咪失敗咯？我睇完呢啲噉嘅施政報告。
我相信仲有啲問題喺法例上邊，我哋未完善。而家嘅法例根本冇辦法杜絕呢啲問題嘅出現。咁所以民主黨一路講，我哋好需要盡快通過一條食水安全法，確保各方面嘅持份者喺。
喺處理水喉食水工程嘅時候，食水水喉嘅安裝工程嘅時候，係冇人係會喺認知不足嘅情況底下，或者佢有意魚目混珠，係令到食水安全咧係受到威脅。當然，我哋都需要確立一個世界嘅標準，係令我哋。
我哋睇到政府水務處做咗好多宣傳，叫我哋珍惜食水。我每次睇到之後咧，我都唔知想喊定想笑。你話我哋每一滴都應該要珍惜，我哋梗係應該要珍惜食水啦。但係水務處而家你又宣傳叫啲人，喂，你最好開水喉夜晚嚇，即係。
因為咧唔保證嗰啲喉管流出嚟嘅水咧係不含誒重金屬或者其他有毒嘅物質，噉你叫公眾點樣相信水務處可以做好把關咧？你叫佢珍惜食水一滴都唔好曬，嗰頭你又叫佢放水，所以我係好心急，我係好希望政府係承諾。
嗱嗱聲幫我哋搞掂呢條食水安全法，但係呢個源水調查報告由五月出版到而家，你哋都仲未正認認真真咁去落實裏邊嘅建議，仲係話啊，我再揾啲專家嚟傾下先，啊，再去研究下咩叫標準先。喂，大佬啊，你拖幾耐啊？其中一項。
運房局，你哋一路過去都冇睇住自己公公屋嗰度嗰啲興建嗰啲嘅水嘅問題。而家你知道有問題啦，好，你叫城建商更換曬呢十一條源水屋村嘅水喉。但係個問題就係你哋話咧，好，我哋換完啲喉之後咧會再驗水嘅，但係我。
咁所以。
跟住呢個食水。
我哋係會全速去進行。
我哋能唔能夠回收多啲香港本身嘅水資源？
然後亦都要密切監察東江水嘅水質嘅。
水塘，我哋仲有冇空間增加存水量？仲有冇機會開拓新嘅水塘？
我哋睇到咧嘅情況就係，我哋根本上有一段好長時間係繼續要依賴東江水嘅。
咁所以我，但係我喺呢度見唔到有咩措施，就係話政府咧會將係全力係增加本地嘅水資源，減少東江水嘅依賴。
主席，我哋關心食水安全。我哋嘅水源係除咗本地嘅水塘，其實我哋好大部分嘅水係嚟自東江水。
當然，我哋係好希望啊，政府係能夠有措施咧，保護我哋本地嘅水源，增加我哋本地嘅水資源。
源水超標委員會提嘅建議咧，係會去落實執行。咁所以，我好希望咧，誒運防局局長咧都係承諾，當換完呢啲喉之後，你抽頭淡水睇下嗰啲喉管有冇出現問題。
海水化碳，我哋知道我哋做緊嘅，但係其實根本上就唔夠。就算起完呢個化海水化碳廠，嗰個每一日嘅供水量啊，都唔夠我哋香港因為喉管老化而漏走咗嘅食水嘅量。
最近我哋亦都睇到一啲報道，係令人非常之擔心，就係話喺東江嘅誒源頭近源頭嗰邊，又再出現咧係垃圾山嘅情況。啲垃圾係周圍堆填，唔單止家居垃圾，有建築垃圾。
關於東江水嘅問題，我喺立法會里邊提出咗好多次，話要上去東江沿岸考察。本來一改再改嘅行程係二月要去嘅，臨時又改咯。而家去到四月啦，噉我希望咧呢個唔會一拖再拖，第三次又再改期。
呢一個問題嚴重到咧，係當地嘅縣政府啊、誒市政府啊，其實咧係解自己解決唔到嘅。噉係咪佢自己包庇咧？我哋唔知道有冇貪污嘅情況，係隻眼開隻眼閉，搞到啲垃圾周圍堆，違反咗佢哋自己內地嘅環境法規。
你既然要得承建商去換咗啲喉之後，你一定咧應該要抽水板，就係抽淨子嘅水板噉，你先至知道嗰啲喉管裏邊仲有冇污染物，污染到食水啊嘛？唔係，然後你哋戇居居嘅運防局，你話啊水嘅嘢我哋唔識嘅，我哋所有嘅嘢係跟。
我梗係唔識笑啦，我梗係想喊啦，因為喺我哋未發現之前，你又已經畀人踢爆，又有工下啲水出咗問題啦。咁所以，我好希望咧，政府唔係承諾話全力跟進，而係你自己政府咧應該出嚟講，就係話我哋一定會定立食水安全法。
係，唔該，主席。
姚崇業議員。
有關。
我係就住。
同我哋做好食水安全嘅把關咧。
施政報告裏邊提到用土地。
作為冇監管嘅官商合作，我係提出反對嘅。
保衞香港食水安全嘅責任，大膽進取一啲加快食水安全立法嘅工作。
施政報告裏邊有關土地、房屋、交通、環境同保育嘅方面咧，係提出我嘅意見嘅。第一，
所以，主席，我講咁多嘢，我係希望新嘅發展局局長馬兆祥先生係可以能夠鼎力孭起咗。
咁雖然我哋話啲水落到嚟香港，我哋可以把關啦，可以濾水廠過濾啦，但事實上，究竟香港知唔知道原來東江沿岸有垃圾山咧？
咁但係個問題，最後要中央派人落到廣東去收拾呢個殘局，嗱嗱聲清理翻啲垃圾，然後堆翻啲泥，係當冇事啦，動個牌話呢度唔準堆垃圾。
如果知道東江沿岸佢哋有人巡查，睇到附近係有一啲違規嘅化工廠又好、垃圾山又好啲可以污染水源嘅嘢都好，係即刻會通報香港，等我哋知道。
因為呢啲噉樣嘅堆填啊，非法堆填係冇做防漏措施，佢嗰啲噉嘅垃圾汁、啲污染物，係絕對有可能污染咗泥土、污染咗東江水，唔單止影響當地嘅居民，亦都會影響我哋香港人。
所以我好希望我哋去睇嘅考察行程咧，係沿岸多啲嘅資訊，我哋可以攞到。但係我哋都唔可能日日都喺上邊㗎。咁究竟東江水有冇一個通報嘅機制？係兩地嘅環境局、兩地嘅水務處會唔會交流情報？
你話我哋係蒙查查唔知㗎，等到有人爆出大件事，可能呢件事我唔知，水務署知唔知，本地嘅環境局知唔知？如果我哋全部都係後知後覺嘅，市民又憑咩相信政府可以喺食水安全嘅問題上邊幫我哋可以及實東江水？
係不得民心。
亦都令到咧。
住宅用地。
係冇辦法。
嘅做法上高咧，已經。
收入同財團合作發展咧。
其實大家有留意最近西九故宮？
喺去超支嘅問題上高，喺去黑箱作業。
我必須要指出呢一種做法啊，係會。
讓西九管理局咧係可以透過呢個土地嘅。
所以係一件非常危險嘅事情，係會完全失控。
讓西九文化管理局可以繞過立法會嘅監管。
落實政府內部有關公司合營守則裏邊嘅規定嘅。
嘅事件啊，都一定會同意。其實整個西九管理局咧。
市民係要求更高嘅透明度同埋更高嘅監察，但係好不幸喺施政報告咧，係倒行逆施，反而提出透過用呢一種冇監管嘅官商合作形式。
出售。
作為融資嘅安排嘅。
係撥畀一個財團。
去經營同埋。
去建造餘下嘅項目嘅。
當時仲搞咗好多展覽。
嗱，大家要回顧一下咧，其實大家應該記得。
所以先至有今日嘅西九管理局。
住宅、酒店嘅用地咧，係作公開。
政府更加係當時向立法會咧承諾咧係以一筆個撥款。
去注資西九管理局，作為興建整個區裏邊嘅項目。
當時政府亦都係承諾咧，係會將西九文化區裏邊有關商業。
但係，因為民間啊，係對用呢一種B.O.T嘅形式咧，有一個官商勾結。
嘅不滿，所以咧最終咧係政府決定放棄用呢一種形式去進行發展西九地區。
而最後咧，亦都得到立法會嘅批准咧，係已經批出咗全數二百一十六億元畀西九管理局作為發展整個項目嘅。
迴歸之後咧，第一次提到將西九發展為文化區嘅時候啊，第一代嘅西九設計咧，當時政府就係提出將整塊四十公頃嘅土地咧，係完全以BOT嘅形式。
施政報告提到，西九文化管理局可以透過一種稱為建造、營運及移交（以下簡稱B.O.T.）嘅方式咧，去同私營嘅機構聯合發展喺西九嘅酒店、辦公室、住。
第二部分係有關房屋。
啲發展西九嘅係決定。
所以今次用BOT嘅形式咧，係絕不可取嘅。
喺西九故宮嘅事件上高咧，佢就向馬會要求捐款。
去唔嚟立法會再嚟申請撥款咧？噉就已經係冇辦法向去問責。
過去幾年不斷犧牲環境，見縫插針，破壞綠化帶。
而嗰個二百一十六億本來就已經係包括曬呢啲項目，噉佢超支又冇辦法。
咁但係佢又唔係嚟失嚟立法會咧，重新申請超支嘅撥款，相反咧。
嗱，但係事隔幾年之後，你會見到咧。而家西九管理局就話已經用曬啲錢啦，而且嚴重超支。
香港嘅樓價紀錄，所以本質上就已經係完全不符合科學精神㗎啦。先講私樓啊。
二千年以嚟嘅按年最高紀錄，而且仲講到話未來三至四年間嘅潛在供應量再創高峯，達到九萬四千火。
但係，大家睇下數字，樓價唔單止冇因為供應量嘅增加而回落，反而繼續上升。過去五年，每年香港都成為全球最難負擔房屋嘅城市。
嗱，如果係呢啲咁亮麗嘅數據啊，如果佢嘅理論係正確，供應增加係可以解決樓價上升嘅，早就已經可以壓抑樓價啦。
而餘下音樂廳嘅建造成本咧，喺今次施政報告裏邊咧，就用BOT嘅形式咧作為注資嘅方法。嗱，咁換句話嚟講，其實就已經係繞過咗立法會嘅監管，亦都漠視咗當年民意反對以BOT形式集資。
梁振英上任之後咧，不斷都係話要增加土地供應嚟壓抑樓價，但係大家好清楚睇到五年好快過去，不單止係冇辦法壓抑到樓價，反而樓價係越升越高，又再破咗。
嘅數字變化。
投資權分開。
仍然無助壓抑樓價。
係話研究郊野公園用地嚟建屋。
其實要解決香港嘅房屋問題。
真正嘅方法就係要將住屋權同埋。
好肯定，好明顯，方法係落錯藥。
大家要記住，呢一個數字係政府喺十一月已經加辣之後。
其實香港現時嘅市區人口密度啊，已經達到每平方公里二萬四千人，係全世界。
清楚反映説明，即使你用埋新蠟焦，即使你所有嘅供應已經大幅上升。
所以落錯約，其實只會進一步破壞環境，令到香港嘅宜居度進一步係更加差。
今次喺施政報告，梁振英唔單止冇去用科學理解究竟點解樓價不斷上升，反而進一步。
差享物業估價處最新公佈，二零一六年十二月嘅住宅價格指數再創新高，達到三百零六點八，比二零一五年同期嘅二百八十五上升咗七個percent。
讓市民真正可以安居樂業，而政府亦都唔怕因為房屋嘅建造成本而會拖垮政府嘅財務承擔。呢個先至係真正解決房屋問題嘅出路。
事實上，差唔多所有嘅經濟學者一致同意，香港嘅樓價高企，實際係因為全球嘅超低息、負實質利率導致熱錢泛濫有關。呢個係投資或者投機嘅需求，而唔係住屋嘅需求。
只係為咗推高建屋量，運房局喺一月底公佈二零一六年全年嘅私人樓宇落成量一萬四千六百夥，按年增長二十九點二個percent。全年私人樓宇施工量二萬五千五百夥，按年係大幅增加八成，創下咗二。
我一直提倡用合作社房屋嘅計劃，令到市民可以選擇。如果佢係唔想投資投機喺房屋，佢唔需要賺，唔會蝕本。政府出地去出建築成本，唔會增加政府嘅建屋嘅融資承擔。
所以咧。
其實。
中土。
一路蠶食。
喺香港，本來。
準備去面對呢一個問題。
第三方面係關於中土嘅問題。
淨我不如又發展埋去啦，嗱最尾咧，其實就係。
大家嘅公共空間，令到香港越嚟越唔適宜居住嘅啫。
但係會因為呢兩年嘅空窗期咧，我哋已經發現有大量嘅新界農地主咧係。
就係政府輸咗一場官司，叫新法案一手造成嘅問題。政府遲遲都冇去糾正自己嘅失誤。
現時已經造成鄉郊嘅嚴重破壞，但係喺施政報告裏邊只係提出以兩年時間去進行中地普查。
市區人口密度其中一個最高嘅城市之一㗎啦，實際上咧已經係令到香港越嚟越不宜居住。即使以平均人口密度咧，亦都達到每平方公里七千人。
大家要諗清楚，當年我哋之所以用高密度發展嘅形式啊，係一種取捨嘅決定。我哋用高密度嘅市區發展換嚟嘅就係能夠保留到我哋較多嘅郊野公園。其實就好似喺一個屋苑。
你既可以揀咧物質質嘅嘅嘅丁屋，亦都可以揀咧幾棟高樓咧換來中間嘅係優化綠化空間。如果而家突冒冒然又話哦，你之前大家共議好嘅寧願高密度換來嘅公共空間咧，而家又話哦有地方。
加快破壞農地，以先破壞後發展，期待兩年之後政府嘅新政策咧可以獲益，變相咧就係鼓勵更多農地主現時加速去破壞新界嘅土地，而政府咧喺回覆我嘅書面質詢嘅時候咧，竟然係話佢哋唔。
報警。
諗住。
而且。
七年都仲未落實。
主席，我想就交通政策發言。
即使係我提出馬上進行凍結調查咧。
嗱，現行嘅機制咧，冇辦法阻止農地變成中地咧。
包括鐵路優先嘅政策，同埋道路擠塞嘅問題。
變相任由新界嘅土地繼續被任意破壞。
政府回覆都係認為不可行，而事實上英國嘅經驗咧，中土優先嘅發展模式底下咧，其實已經係可以。
搞到而家咧，新界隨處都係泥頭山、石屎化嘅農地，政府嘅回覆係話沒有執管權。
呢一種荒謬嘅現象咧，必須要馬上糾正。我會計劃提出私人草案修改城市規劃條例，希望重新回到有執管權嘅城市規劃狀況。
阻止嘅行行動嘅，而好明顯，現時有大量嘅中地作業咧，都係污染泥土、污染空氣、污染河道嘅。所以其實政府係有責任去執行有關違反地契條款嘅行為嘅。
農地不斷變成中地咧，對生態環境係百害而無一利，影響香港嘅生物多樣性。而政府啱啱就係出咗文件咧，就係想確保香港嘅生物多樣性咧係得以改善，所以其實係背道而馳嘅。
好快脆就已經解決到中地嘅問題嘅。大家留意咧，其實根根據新法案嘅判詞咧，只要證明到中地作業係屬於令人厭惡嘅用途啊，其實就已經屬於違反地契條款，係可以採取。
係因為城市規劃條例裏邊嘅漏洞，但係我哋到而家都未見到政府有任何嘅係計劃咧，係去修訂城市規劃條例。事實上，政府喺二千年嘅時候係承諾過市民咧係會進行第二階段嘅諮詢，但係一拖再拖，已經十。
鐵路嘅競爭者。
係會有危險嘅。
鐵路嘅系統因事故而唔。
過分集中依賴鐵路服務咧。
市民仲可以有選擇，可以有替代。
乘客受到連鎖效應嘅影響。
例如有壞車啊，或者其他嘅系統問題咧。
亦都令到巴士同埋小巴而家唔再係。
人數係數以萬計，甚至數以十萬計嘅。
噉啊！但係我係發覺呢個鐵路優先嘅政策咧，近年咧似乎開始變質。
如果小巴同埋鐵路唔係削，小巴同埋巴士唔係削減得咁緊要。
誒而家香港政府咧係以鐵路為優先，作為個交通嘅重要政策。
好多時候，因為一啲即係小嘅事故，就要令到一啲主要嘅車站咧要封閘啊，要做人流管制啊。
當有新嘅鐵路線開通嘅時候，隨之而嚟嘅就係削減巴士同埋小巴嘅服務，令到基層嘅市民受好大嘅影響。
現時鐵路系統每日已經超過五百人、五百萬人次使用，佔公共交通嘅總運輸量接近四十二個percent。
誒變成傾斜於鐵路呢種變質咧，甚至係趕絕咗好多其他嘅交通工具，包括巴士啦、小巴。
作為一個重要嘅。
道路基建咧係追唔上。
噉啊！正如我頭先講啦。
而家香港嘅塞車咧，越嚟越嚴重啊！
唔能夠過分依賴鐵路系統。
第二方面，主席，我想講一講香港嘅道路擠塞嘅問題。
如果有壞車等等造成嘅擠塞咧，更加嚴重。
主要係因為車輛嘅數目增長得非常之快。
一到繁忙時間咧，塞車就好嚴重。就以北區為例。
講緊係時速五公里，仲行仲慢過行路啊！
交通政策嘅一員，亦都係誒鐵路嘅競爭者。
所以，我認為政府有必要重新檢討交通工具嘅政策。
私家車數目增長係造成道路擠塞嘅主要原因。我哋睇翻數據，零六年一月。
例如公共運輸策略研究往後嘅措施等等，應該要加強翻巴士、小巴甚至渡輪嘅角色。
幾個主要嘅交匯處喺繁忙時間經常塞車，一塞塞一個鐘頭兩個鐘頭，喺偏遠地區嘅居民苦不堪言。
喺二零一四年交諮會公佈嘅香港道路交通擠塞研究報告就提到，當時早上繁忙時間部分嘅路段行車嘅車速。
但係。
喺古洞。
尤其係。
我哋希望政府有關當局。
但係你都要處理受影響嘅居民。
新界東北發展，我明白係需要做嘅。
老人院一帶嘅住緊嘅院友。
突如其來嘅東北發展，令到佢哋枕蓆不安。
領牌私家車平均嘅增長咧，係由零六年。
呢個數目已經係超過四十九萬二千五百架。
私家車嘅數目係三十六萬架，去到今年嘅十月。
呢啲長者已經七老八十，本身係希望喺嗰個院舍裏邊安享晚年。
十年期間增長三個percent，去到一零到一三年咧，個增長率就去到四點八個percent。
誒喺呢個期間，十四萬三千個新增嘅牌照當中咧，私家車係佔九成二。
我哋認為咧，有必要制定一套長遠限制車輛增加嘅政策，同時咧要確立翻公共交通工具能夠有道路優先使用權嘅原則。
最後啊，主席，我亦都想借呢個機會咧，就同發展局局長誒再講一講。啊，閣下同誒勞福局局長咧，亦都啱啱榮升啦。噉啊，我亦都當面同阿局長講過。
石禮謙而。
多謝主席，本人緊止參政。
First, I like to talk about housing.
真係要考慮一下呢批老人家嘅福祉。
Without a doubt, the current term government has made strenuous efforts in this area.
As the 2017 C election is approaching, the public seems to be more interested.
The prime concern of our citizens and the top priority of the successive SAR government.
在誰將成為下一位首席執行官？在李家超的最後政策演講中。
社會和諧，讓一般公眾會能過上和平與滿足的生活，在可見的未來。
亦都考慮到佢哋同現在經營者密不可分嘅關係，喺制定有關安置嘅政策嘅時間。
Thank you, Mr President. Mr President, I shall be using thirty minutes of my allocated time to speak on the policy address as a whole.
是，的relative co-shoulder given to this policy address， alluding that people have already transferred their hopes to Mr. Siowai Long's successor。
係切實可行噉樣去令到呢啲老人家得以安心去搬去政府而家準備興建新嘅安老院舍大樓。
this might be lamentable, but from tackling our housing woes, fostering wealth creation to improve governance, this policy address.
yet what it has achieved still falls short of public expectations. It's rather sad, but they did try very hard. Concerning public housing, there are around 290,000 applicants on the waiting list.
Like Mr. C.Y. Like Mr. C.Y. Lung's previous four, has no breakthroughs that could guide Hong Kong out of the economic stonewave and re-inject a sense of hope and confidence about creating a society of stability, prosperity and.
係。
floods.
confusing and overly aggressive.
has been impaired, sadly so.
consequently, elderly family members of these.
which in turn affected the turnover of the public rental housing units.
However, the crux of the problem might be attributed to the S.A.R. governments.
措施，for example， allow white form buyers to purchase second-hand HOS。
rental housing applicants have also extended from three years of waiting to 4.7 years during the same period.
The unresolved supply-demand mismatch of the public rental housing units has been one of the factors leading to the worsening situation.
先生，提供公共 housing 是 aim to promote social harmony by allowing the needy to live in peace and contentment.
PRH tenants are forced to live alone. This is inconsiderate and inconsistent with our Chinese traditions, such as respect of family values and filial piety.
The housing ladder, of public rental housing, home ownership scheme and the private flats, are as a conventional means for citizens to improve their living conditions, subject to their financial capability.
have disrupted the secondary market of the home ownership scheme flats, which was originally designated for eligible green form buyers. Consequently, the chance of public rental housing tenants purchasing HOS flats is reduced.
for the public rental housing units. Compare with 190 applicants in March 2012, there has been a surge of over 100,000 applicants since Mr. Siow Long took office. The average waiting time of the general public.
sadly, many public rental housing families are forced to split and relocate under the current policy of housing splitting, as their younger family members have entered the job market, when increased family income makes such families fail the means test.
幹預。
政府， primary objective。
則係一個扭曲的市場需求和物價。
court keep driving up our property prices, despite the government's
On public rental housing units available for the public rental housing applicants.
of its housing policy is not to help every individual to purchase a home.
An active property market, free from unnecessary interference, will reflect the true state rather.
Its harsh measures have undermined, have undermined the self-adjusting mechanism of the property market.
這 major setback exposes the government's lack of understanding of the property market, as well as its incompetence.
market is the only solution to stabilise property prices and restore the balance between supply and demand of residential properties.
shorter and shorter. The strong rebound of public prices after each of these interventions reflected the resilience of the market. It's not subject to government control. You cannot control the government, the market.
as well as causing inconvenience to people's daily life, creating show show this harmony and not for the purpose of harmony. Although these far from people-oriented policies might help the housing society to embellish its figures.
While the government's elderly policy highlights ageing in the community and continuum of care, both the policy of house splitting for tackling the underoccupation and the policy of well-off tenants have been undermining the said Chinese tradition.
for private housing. Over the past few years, the government have introduced measures to curb the surging property prices. The last year, however, low low global interest rates imbalance between supply and demand for private flats and high construction.
From SSD to BSD, DSD and the latest increase in AVD rates, each time a cooling period was created, with a slight drop in property prices and a sharp reduction in property transactions in the second hand market. But the effort becomes
政府必須盡力，確保他們不遺餘力地滿足基層和中下階層的住房需求，透過興建更多出租屋和H.O.S.公寓，以更迅速的辦法。
係。
given a different review.
local communities。
香港應該 improve its planning.
that the town planning board should be.
例如，的組成，的城鄉規劃委員會。
and development. If the government not going to do this within this four year, I will be trying to move.
私人 housing應該被留給 invisible hand of the market， with minimum interference。
on the contrary, many many old urban districts have been brutally segregated and demolished.
作為結果，城市更新項目非常 often，fail to improve the overall living conditions of all urban districts.
We are now in the 21st century, but our land use planning is not commensurate with what a developed city should be like.
Urban renewal, on the other hand, is conducted on a project basis without adequate consideration of the cohesiveness and harmony of the local community.
needs to be reformed drastically. The current arrangement of both the chairman and vice chairman of the town planning board are government officials is unpalatable.
什麼政府應該做的是確保適當規劃和穩定供應，以滿足不同社會階層人民的住房需求。
Town planning ordinance need to be amended so that a non-official representative, instead of the director of planning, shall be appointed as vice chairman and etc. to ensure adequate consideration of innovative approaches to planning.
However, this is easier said than done, Mr. President. It is a shame that the SAR government has still embraced the mentality of the seventy s and eighty s to formulate a strategy on planning and land development today. My fellow lawmakers, in their absentee.
back burner。
conversely.
affordable market.
要將這個主題作為他們的首要經濟政策。
長遠，wealth creation for the short to medium term， which has been
most relishing is again left blank or put on a a.
After the link have been taken over, their their their the all this government's property.
SAR政府必須put a stop to destructive patterns of thinking in planning and urban renewal.
Perhaps Mr. Siwai Leung banks on the concept of reindustrialisation. However, it is unlikely to be realised in the short to medium term.
Are destroyed since rentals and property prices have escalated. Follow the urban renewal, just like the public rental housing tenants that they were deprived of.
主席，persistent well-being of a city and its people hinges on sustainable economic development of the city. Therefore, wealth creation must be the primary concern of the government. To our dismay.
Need for the public space and better air quality. It is the irreversible malpractice of the government which neglects urban layout and hampers quality of living and convenience of the people, as it has been hopelessly conservative and bureaucratic.
The SAR government has only focused on increasing land supply, but failed desperately to consider the long-term and healthy development of the city as a coherent whole. The accusation of blindly usurping the land is not simply about how the government overlooks the.
The CE's last policy address, like his previous four, have failed to address this issue adequately. Whilst the CE stress on the national 13 five five year plan and the belt and rope expresses his good intention of promoting economic growth and health for the long.
Mr. Siow Long setting up, setting a hard target on settling the working hour policy and the MPF offsetting mechanism. Within this term of the government, would risk putting the next CE in danger of being a lame duck in those areas almost.
從這次開始，下一次行政，如果達成硬目標導致僵硬，而同時加重我們的營商環境，特別是中小企業，的傷害，而這在近年已經惡化，是時候讓四個候選人角逐下一次歐盟理事會選舉。
這些 worry 是 not baseless。
When it comes to education.
system to nurture such talents.
As no concrete plans and target are provided.
一花port，一fresh，花port，和一cyberport。
Although our education expenses continue to rise year after year.
關於如何來實質化再工業化。
先生，一 recent report of the Academy of Science of Hong Kong reviews that the since the implementation of the current
Our education system remains problem-ridden. The problem lies in the officials in charge of our education policy. We should have
But is reindustrialisation itself just another slogan, like Mr. Tong's developing Hong Kong as a Chinese medicine hub?
It is doubtful that the development of innovative and technology industry and the concept of reindustrialisation will bear fruits.
在開場句子，Mr. President， of the policy address， paragraph 54， Mr. C.Y. Leung said， innovation and technology are no slogan。
作為結果，Faculty of Science and Engineering has relatively more difficulty in admitting students with good academic result. If this trend sustains,
diploma for secondary education in Hong Kong (HKDSE), fewer students have enrolled in STEM-related subject science, technology, engineering and mathematics, and many high-performing students opted to study medicine, business or law at universities.
Moreover, we are ill-prepared to implement re-industrialisation by which the C.E. hope to foster smart production and technology research and development in Hong Kong, because Hong Kong lacks not only a pool of talents for re-industrialisation, but also our education.
Anthony to be the head of that because he has the experience. He has been teaching and he has been a chancellor. They have been neither. They have neither vision nor mission, as mere pseudo educationists who know little about the essence of education.
This probably will enable the next government.
That the government has done little to address properly.
The SAR government should treat education spending not as an expenditure.
exploration of uncharted waters, of knowledge, in education.
We should also build more student hostel. At the moment, there are eight thousand six hundred.
Mr. President, while education attainment is important in a knowledge-based society, education attainment is not everything.
which is about nurturing all-round educated people, that will suit the needs of a modern knowledge-based society.
As a second language curriculum for non-Chinese speaking students to cater for the non-Chinese speaking needs, these are just a few of the important issues.
但作為一個重要的投資，在培育人力資本，為產生一永續的未來收入，為城市的永續性。
我 like to touch on the surplus. Thanks to the former FS for his nine and a half years of hard work to build up a fiscal reserve of over nine hundred billion dollars.
since一九九七， admission of secondary students to the eight university have not increased and stay at fifteen thousand. Whereas every year we have approximately twenty two thousand, seven thousand are left places.
Given BCA will continue to be a device only for education bureau to rank primary schools and secondary school, this will drag schools, parents and students in endless loop of drilling. Such practice must be discontinued.
教育不是關於達成各種指標，教育不是關於釋放每，教育是關於釋放每個人的潛能，教育過程應該不是一場無聊的鑽研，應該是一場挑戰。
Mr President, sky is the limit. With this in mind, neither the TSA, the territory-wide system assessment, nor its recently modified version of Basic Competency Assessment (BCA) serve any meaningful purpose in education.
要取一個更積極的態度來緩解教育的投資不足問題，降低中學教師學生比，擴大補助的學位數量，每年讓更多資格合格的學生進入本科課程。目前
flat hostile places a major problem and this actually in prevent us from taking any overseas student and review funding of the we should also carry out a review funding methods of the UGC to foster internationalism of local university to develop Chinese.
and this.
Now I turn to the shortage of.
我係非常 happy 講 to him and convince him.
was similarly, it's not nothing wrong when he.
Every dollar increase will be reflected in the price of our flats.
labour，particularly in the construction industry， in this year policies address
And impose a limit on the development of human capital to certain industry only.
to Mr. C E back to Dover, as the cost per per square foot.
actually sees patients. It's just like a different way of making a business, but the the problem with our rising
of the construction cost per square foot have risen from 3,000 to 5,000 during the period of the last four years.
Gokake was complaining about developers buying land. What's problem of developers buying land? As long as they are legal and transparent.
Prices in flats is because of the greediness of government. This high land policy, price policy, like every every in every transactions, the government wants the highest.
CE stated that whilst the land price is rising and rising, that is unacceptable. But then he further stated that the construction cost has gone up, but is acceptable.
While we used to be complaining about Hong Kong's economic structure for its lack in diversity, the construction industries underachievers with an alternative path to climb up the social economic ladder. Nevertheless, under the influence of our education system and traditional beliefs, young people are reluctant.
to enter into the construction industries, as parents and the children and their children have a general obsession that only become a professional like doctor, lawyer, banker will provide them with more promising and secure future. Such obsession kills the potential and possibilities of our younger gen.
And the developers are only there with a high price land policy. We can only produce with rising construction costs. What we can make little profit of it. So I hope that Gokake should understand this. If he have problem understanding a simple like simple issue like this, he can talk.
因。
and die with dignity.
and resulting the erosion of public.
一 caring society should be distinguished.
They contribute towards the growth of the GDP and its economy.
They have basically they they have as as many imported labour as the population.
should be stepped up to train local caretakers and to speed up importation of labour to fill the manpower gap of the sector.
從 indiscriminate welfareism， which tends to sap individual responsibility and incentive to work。
Look at Macau, how they have resolved the problem of development. They imported labour, and look at Singapore.
with a view to improving the service quality of this care home and allow and allowing the elderly and the disadvant disadvantage to live.
Mr. President, in an affluent society like Hong Kong, building up a caring society is not incompatible with stress on economic development.
It is unacceptable for government to allow four to five thousand elderly citizens to die every year while on the waiting list for a place in a subsidised nursing home.
pers， building up a caring society should be viewed as a reflection of the government respect of humanity that an that an advanced economy should always emphasise.
The current supplementary labour scheme is not up to scratch, as has indicated in his two hundred and one six policy address. The C E said the government will review the effectiveness of the enhancement measure under the supplementary labour scheme to ensure sustainable development of construction industry.
Mr. C.E. The construction industry and I have been longing for your favourable reply. We are very short of labour. Just look at the express rail. One of the major problems that they have encountered is the shortage of labour. Look at Sengkang.
This is a shame to a society like us. The SAR government should take more proactive approach to building more subsidised residential cares home and allocating more resources to offer timely care for the socially disadvantaged, such as the elderly and the mentally challenged, particularly efforts.
before the handover， Hong Kong used to be。
Used to have very little, if not zero, policy risk.
簡短，的問題可以歸結到問題的治理。
Members, that the government today could hardly use its clout to influence public opinions.
先生，我贊同The Efforts of the Chief Executive and This Administration。
unanimous tone of explanation to convince the public and minimise the impacts.
Over the past four years, little progress have been made in resolving Hong Kong's deep-seated conflicts.
On issues of major concern, but what makes matters worse is the S.A.R. government even failed to offer a unanimous tone.
Arguably, the current term government is the worst in the history of SAR for as far as handling executive-legislative relationship is concerned.
Responsibility and mind their own business and assume responsibility only for matters concerning their own policy area. How could it be possible for a government to achieve good governance under bureaucracy like this?
If I has instigated so many times in our PAC report, the weakest link, I consider, lies in the incompetence of the administration and the self-conceitness of some of our top officials.
Communication between the administration and the council is apparently insufficient. Not to mention lobbying with the opposition camp, the administration have even failed to communicate and collaborate with the pro-establishment camp effectively.
Very often, officials of the incumbent government take it for granted that we, the pro-establishment lawmakers, must support the SAR government and toe its line. Bureaus and departments, on the other hand, lack cooperation and coordination, as exposed in the Wangjiao saga. The lead water
incident, the joint consultation of the SFC and the Hong Kong Exchange about the proposed reform of the Hong Kong listing policy, the handling of the Wakan School premises, to name just a few. It seems that the officials daily practices to shrink duty, and its.
In that the colonial government championed water type policy planning, the rule of law, free market principle, a level playing field, a business friendly environment, etc. When government policies or initiatives were deviant from these core values, the government of the day would offer a.
On investors and the society, they have helped the colonial government create a general perception that the government seemed fair, open, reasonable and predictable. Arguably, things have become more complex today with the advancement of information technology around the legislators.
現在等。
The right time to get rid of.
明天九點鐘續會。
Of hope, provided that we uphold the basic law and our core values. Thank you, Mr. President.
Of explanation most of the time, when it comes to putting forward government policy and funding proposals, while the opposition destructive filibusters in recent years must be condemned and condemned.
Seriously, that they have actually affected Hong Kong well-being. Ill-prepared officials who tend to answer the legislature queries in drips and drabs manner are equally reproachable in politics perception.
是everything。如果CE政策 makers和the officials are confused and fail to convince themselves， how could the public and investor be convinced of the SAR government is fair、open、reasonable and predictable？Mr President， the looming policy risk have been under。
Hong Kong as Asia's world city and as an international financial centre. Nonetheless, despite Mr. Siu Y Long's verbosity, his last policy address, being the longest one since the Hanover, lacks practical antidote to this menace, which should be first dealt with by getting rid of.
And improve governance. Some people said that the next CEO should be one who is capable of helping the government to put out the fire. A metaphor means to resolve controversies, disputes, conflict. Nevertheless, as the adage goes, prevention is always better than cure. Why didn't the government
Take every precaution to prevent fire in the first place, instead of allowing fire set by the government itself times and times again. So the ultimate solution lies in tackling the deep-seated bureaucracy that has been taken root in the S.A. government over the past two decades. It will be a concerted
bureaucacy. A smooth transition is necessary for facilitating the next administration to handle this task. Rather than running against the clock to try to achieve as many things as possible, that could risk creating more problem for the next administration. Mr. C. E. should, in the twilight of his tenure, devote
促進調解和解決爭議和衝突。Mr. President，我們可以失去信心，但我們不能失去希望。Hopefully，概念一國兩制和高度自治以及人民治理香港的願景在基本法中，將保護我們免於被耗盡。